So, if you've ever wondered why your ice
cream turns out gummy, excessively icy,
sticky, and sometimes sandy, today's
video might help you, cuz we're going to
talk about ice cream stabilizers, how to
use them, how much to use, and whether
you even need them in the first place.
I get a lot of questions and a lot of
requests for doing videos for ice cream
stabilizers. I use them in most ice
creams. I'm not going to lie. So, what
do they actually do as well? You know,
before we go too deep into this subject,
is ice cream stabilizers. Stabilizers as
a whole. Ice cream stabilizers is a
generic term where an ingredient is
added to do something to your base.
Usually, that is to increase viscosity
and grab hold of some of that free water
and turn it into a slightly better mouth
fill. Give your ice cream longevity in
the freezer. reduce the size of the ice
crystal formation and prevent things
like weighing off where your dairy
separates into the solids and the whey
as it melts. It's quite unattractive in
a commercial environment.
You really don't need to use a lot of
stabilizer in ice creams. anywhere from
0.1% up to about 0.5% depending on your
recipe, what it is you're making, how
much you're making, fat percentage,
sugar percentage, all these kind of
things dictate how much you need to use.
Because these numbers are so small, 0.1%
is a tiny amount for your recipe. Let's
talk about guar and zantham gum. If you
want or if you need your recipe needs
one gram of zanthan gum and you measure
that by a teaspoon then even if you are
half a gram out that will be the
difference between your ice cream being
really nice texture with good longevity
and excellent mouth feel and super gummy
slightly slimy and really quite
unpleasant to eat. So it has a huge
effect just using half a gram quarter of
a gram too much. Commercial gums are
super strong and you can use them in
lots of other recipes as well. And they
are used in gluten-free recipes quite
often because they increase viscosity.
They hold on and bind ingredients
together.
So any ice cream stabilizer that you
want to use, you need to use it
properly. And that is number one. You
need to disperse that into your other
solids. So, your powders, your sugars,
sugar substitutes, milk powder, put your
stabilizer into that and stir it up to
get rid of all those clumps and lumps of
ice cream stabilizer. If they end up in
the dairy or in the liquid, they will
not break up. They will just stay in a
little clump and they won't do anything
at all. And then when you train your ice
cream, you might end up breaking that
clump apart and just have a little
selection of powder.
There is a synergistic effect between
some stabilizers such as gooa, locust
bean gum, carrageenins that when you
start combining these ingredients
together, they they work together in
synergy to better your ice cream in a
much better way than just using one of
them. The list is almost endless, but in
another video we'll go through the
synergistic effect. I've touched on this
in the past, but we'll do another video
on it moving forward. As I've said, too
much of an ice cream stabilizer will
ruin your batch and make it super
sticky, gummy, and really horrible and
unpleasant to eat. So, you've got to
weigh it properly. And I recommend a
little small scale such as this. And
they're super cheap. I I think you can
pick these up for less than $10 on
Amazon, less than £10 in the UK. So,
it's worth investing in something like
that if you're going to get into ice
cream stabilizers.
So, let's talk about gua. Gua gum or gua
gum if you're in the US. Um, it's very
strong. It is a cold process stabilizer
means it hydrates between 50 and 60°
centigrade, which is this in Fahrenheit.
But that said, it will also hydrate
completely in about 10° centigrade
liquids. It will just take a much longer
period of time. Usage is quite low. So,
0.1% is where I would start depending on
what I'm making. If I'm making a gelato,
so lower fats, then you will need more
stabilizer because there's much less
milk solids in your recipe. So go up in
small increments with gu. It's excellent
at increasing viscosity and it works in
synergy with locust bean gum. Gu is also
incredibly good value for money compared
to other commercial stabilizers. And a
little goes a long way. So if you bought
200 g of guar, it would last you years.
I use guar a lot on cold processed. I
prefer that over zantham, but there is a
time to use zantham. And that time is
when you're looking at acidic bases.
Guard doesn't work well in acidic based
ice creams. Things like pineapple,
apple, you know, lemons, oranges, all
those kind of things. Guard isn't great
in acidic environments. You're much
better off using zantham.
[Music]
Zantham again is a cold process
stabilizer, so it completely hydrate in
lower temperatures. It doesn't need
superheating. The amount you would use
is slightly less than guard because it
is a really strong gum for viscosity
change. And with that in mind, it can
give you a slimy mouth feel if you use
too much of it.
[Music]
Next, we're going to talk about locust
bean gum. It's got a really weird ass
name, but it's very normal. It's from
the locust bean tree. This does need
heating. It only hydrates above 80°
centigrade. So between 80 and 90 is this
perfect little environment, which is why
I recommend heating bases up to 85°
centigrade if you're using a hot
processed stabilizer. The amount you'd
use again depends on your recipe and the
combination of other stabilizers that
you use. But if you just use locus bean
gum, which I do quite a lot, and to be
fair, then you can increase the amount
up to 0.2.3%
without any real major issues. It
actually forms a gel when it's heated
and hydrated. That gel increases the
viscosity of your base and creates a
slightly more elastic feel, which is
what we often perceive in gelato when we
buy from the store. Locus gum is
excellent on its own, but it does work
even better when you combine it with gua
or carragean.
So carrageenan,
specifically the kappa and lambda
variations, incredibly low dosage on
these, 0.01%, 01%
you know up to kind of 0.05%. It's a
really really small amount. You cannot
measure that in a spoon. You need that
little micro scale. It also needs
hydrating above 70° centigrade. So
perfect hydration temperature for the
carragean group is around 80 centrade
which is this in Fahrenheit. And it
needs to be kept there for about 10 to
15 minutes. So that's something you need
to consider. Just heating your your base
up to that temperature is one thing, but
then you need to start keeping it at
that base to completely hydrate your
stabilizer. Capacarragean forms a gel.
Lambda doesn't form a gel. So that will
be important depending on what ice cream
you're making. They prevent weighing
off, which means the whey part of your
dairy starts to melt and seep out first
as your ice cream is there in a bowl.
And sometimes when you look in ice cream
that you buy from the store or you go
out and have some from a scoop shop and
you'll see a clear liquid or
semi-transparent liquid, that's the way
coming out of that dairy. There's
nothing wrong with it, but it's just not
a particularly attractive thing to see.
So that's where the use of carrageans
come in.
Caroxymethylulose
or CMC, sometimes known as cellulose
gum. It's got a hideous name for a
start. It shouldn't make any difference
to us if you're using stabilizers. CMC
is very commonly used in commercial
environments because it's pretty cheap.
Dosage rates are about the same as most
of the others from 0.2 to 0.5%. And it
does need fully hydrating above 75
centrade as well. The difference being
to completely hydrate it needs in excess
of 20 minutes at that temperature. So
you're going to need to keep that base
at that temperature for that length of
time. So you then need to calculate in
evaporation rates as well. So, that's
something you need to consider if you're
going to go down the ice cream
stabilizer route is not only the
hydration temperature, the hydration
time, and the amount of water
evaporation that you're going to get for
that length of time. CMC is a strong
water binder, so it holds onto water for
deer life, and it will increase
viscosity really well. It prevents
excessive ice crystal growth, but to be
fair, nearly all of them do that anyway.
It does improve longevity of your ice
cream incredibly well, which is why
commercial makers often use it, but it
can create a really weird pasty kind of
texture if you overuse it.
[Music]
Tarum. Taragam is excellent. It's one of
my favorites because you can use it as
it is with no other additional
stabilizers. Slightly lower dosage rate,
0.1% upwards, but it is like a catch all
stabilizer. It does most things that
most other stabilizers do, just not
quite as well. So, it's like a jack of
all trades, if you will. It hydrates
above 75 centigrade. So, 75 to 85
centigrade. So, it does need proper
heating and it will need to be
maintained at that temperature for 15 to
20 minutes. So, again, you need to
calculate that in along with your
evaporation. It's somewhere in between
guar and locust bean gum as far as
stability is concerned. That means how
much water it will hold on to, how much
viscosity it will increase by. But it is
also a clean label version on or a clean
label alternative to locust bean gum. It
is also synergistic with carrageenan and
zantham gum. So you can get benefits by
combining those stabilizers.
Sodium algenate really low dosage rate
0.1 to 0.3%. Anything more than that and
you start to get a really weird mouth
feel. It is a cold process stabilizer so
thickens in cold liquid. You can heat it
up if you need to dissolve other solids
such as sugar in your ice cream base. I
wouldn't take it above 70° centigrade
because then it starts to change its
function. Sodium algenate actually forms
a gel when in the presence of calcium.
So calcium obviously in dairy. So
generally it's not used in that
environment especially on highfat ice
creams. And this is where the gel and no
gel argument comes into place. You do
not need to create a gel in highfat
recipes. you might consider wanting to
create a gel in a low-fat or ultra low
fat recipe. And that's what I did
before. Used a combination of
stabilizers to create a gel in synergy
to increase the viscosity and better the
mouth feel.
Gelatin. Gelatin is another clean label
stabilizer. Dosage rates can be slightly
higher up to 0.8% 8% if required. But
again, you need to know why you're going
up that high before you just dump loads
in. Gelatin will melt at about 50 to 55°
centigrade, which is this in Fahrenheit.
And again, with some of the others, you
need to maintain that temperature for 15
to 20 minutes. That's a soaking time or
a melt time, depending on the type of
gelatin that you use. And that is why
you will often find gelatin sheets that
are soaked for 15 to 20 minutes before
using them. They are then processed into
liquids and then you've got that soaking
time. The gelatin has then dispersed
within that liquid quite easily. But if
you're using powdered gelatin, then you
need to bring the heat up, dissolve that
powder, make sure it's incorporated with
your sugars before you start mixing into
liquid. If you dump gelatin powder into
liquid, it just sits on the top, turns
into balls, and makes an absolute mess.
onto agar. AAR is becoming more popular
to use. It's got really low dosage
rates, 0.1% to 0.3%. It needs boiling
almost, so it's incredibly high heating
temperature, 90° centigrade upwards, so
it's incredibly high, not good for a lot
of ice cream recipes cuz you will burn
the dairy if you're not careful. And it
needs to maintain that temperature for
10 minutes as well. There are a lot of
catch all stabilizers that have agar in
it, but that's that's because some
recipes will need heating higher than
others, and that's what they put that in
for to try and catch certain heating
temperatures to make sure that the
result is as good as it can get. It
creates a really strong gel. So, you can
actually make jellies with aar, but it
can also make the texture brittle. And
sometimes when you scoop an ice cream
and you see the surface break up into
layers, that is what happens when you
create a brittle ice cream based on
using stabilizers the wrong way. It's
not so much bad to eat cuz once it
starts to melt in your mouth, those
layers break up anyway, but it does mean
that the mouth fill isn't as good as it
could be.
On to pectin. Both types, same kind of
dosage range, 0.1 to 0.3% by weight.
high hydration temperatures, 80 to 90
degrees centiggrade. Again, like a lot
of other stabilizers. It's kind of as
high as you want to go. I wouldn't go
above 90 really, but you also need to
keep it there for 10 to 15 minutes. So,
it's it's pretty good actually. I don't
mind using pectin. Pectin is really
nice. Um, it creates a a really smooth,
silky kind of mouth feel. It creates a
gel, but it's quite mild, so it doesn't
get brittle like some of the others do.
And it's all often used or most often
used in sorbes and fruitbased recipes.
simply because its chemical makeup is
perfect for integrating into those. It's
clean. There's the perfect amount of
viscosity change for fruits and sorbes.
So, pectin is great for those.
Conjac gum. It's becoming more popular
because of certain viral ice cream
videos that have used it. Normal dosage
rate 0.1 to 0.3%. hydration temperature
85° centigrade upwards with a hydration
time of 10 to 20 minutes. So, you're
keeping your dairy really high in
temperature for a long period of time.
And if you're not careful and you use
the wrong amount, it will go like flour
paste. It's a really strong jelling
ability. And if you've ever made a rue,
that's kind of what you're doing here.
You're heating up to create this super
hyper thickened base with a slightly
strange texture. So be careful when
using conjract gum. Uh it's quite
difficult to buy in most places. So I
could personally I I don't use it. I
wouldn't buy it. But depending on what's
available in your country, in your area,
if that's what's available, then you
might want to consider trying it.
So like I said before, blending some of
these stabilizers creates a synergistic
effect where the best of both worlds
combined to create something that works
in tandem. So you know your carrage and
weighing off in combination with your
locust bean gum will create a really
super nice texture ice cream. You
combine that with a little bit of goo as
well as well and you've got a better
viscosity increase with much better
mouth fill and ice crystal formation
from the locus bean gum to the lack of
weighing off from the carrageans. You've
got this little balance that happens. So
you might want to start consider that if
considering that if you're making on a
home environment and you want to use a
gum, I personally would just start with
either gua or tara gum. Um tar gum would
be my preferred but it is incredibly
expensive and quite difficult to get
hold of in some places. I get mine from
Europe and I import it because it's just
insanely expensive over here and I think
the US prices are increasing
exponentially for one reason or another.
So that's something to consider. Guar
and Zantham are available pretty much
everywhere. You can buy them on Amazon
for not a lot of money. Out of the two,
I would absolutely use Gu more than
Zantham, but if you make a lot of acidic
recipes, then Zantham is the one to go
for. Just watch the amounts that you
use. I find Zantham, even a tiny amount
too much, will just create a mouth feel
that I'm I'm not overly keen on. I also
want to mention about the overheating
and extended heating of stabilizers. If
you are going to use them, pay attention
to the heating temperature requirements
and the time requirements. If you're
unsure if you can stand there for 10 to
15 minutes to make sure that that
stabilizer completely hydrated, keep the
temperature the same, but reduce the
time because if you heat a base up to 85
centigrade to hydrate a stabilizer, it
will start the hydration process right
away as you're creeping up to that
temperature, it will then do it as it's
cooling down as well. And there's a like
a drop off temperature. Every stabilizer
has a drop off temperature.
And that drop off temperature is when it
stops hydrating. So once it's been
hydrated, the cell walls open and then
it starts to create that viscosity
change or whatever it is that it's
doing. Once you reach that drop off
temperature, then it will stop the
cells. The cell will shrink back down.
But the majority of the work is already
done by that point. So you don't really
have a lot to worry about. So get it up
to the temperature even just for 5
minutes will be enough to hydrate most
heat activated stabilizers.
Cold activator stabilizers like guar and
zantham, you must be careful when you
heat them up. If you heat them up to 50°
centiggrade, that's fine. Don't heat it
up past that and don't heat it up for
that temperature for too long cuz what
you will do is you'll create something
super thick, incredibly viscous and the
result will be a really unpleasant mouth
feel and gummy, weird, slimy textures.
So, you've got to be careful with cold
process stabilizers.
Finally, the importance of resting an
ice cream base. Some people are in a
rush. You know, everyone's life is
different. If you're in a rush and you
don't want to age your base in the
fridge overnight and you want to bring
the temperature down in an ice bath nice
and quick and get it in your machine,
that totally fine. That's absolutely up
to you. But you are missing a couple of
things. You're missing flavor boosting
from the aging process. And you're also
missing that extended period of
hydration. Uh, all stabilizers will
benefit from prop hydration. So that
that means don't rush them. And you can
you can really make a difference by
allowing an ice cream base to age in the
refrigerator overnight. It makes a huge
difference as far as texture is
concerned and mouth feel because that
viscosity changes. And you will notice
it if you make two identical batches and
then you have one that ages overnight
and one that doesn't. You will see a
very distinct change as you churn them
up. And what I am going to do is I'm
going to on Patreon I'm going to put a
chart that you can download that tells
you the stabilizer the usage approximate
usage level and the hydration
temperatures and times. You can download
that, print that off, you keep it on
your phone on wherever you want to keep
it and it's a good reference chart which
means that depending on what one you're
using, you know exactly how much to use,
what temperature to heat it to, and for
how long. So hopefully that will be of
use to you guys. Again, bit of a talky
one, but so many people ask me about
stabilizers. If you don't want to use
them, then you absolutely don't have to.
Will a custard create the same kind of
mouth feel?
No, it won't. It will create a different
mouth feel. Custard will create a lovely
texture because of the lesserin that
you're adding into that. And lesserin
just bonds liquids and fats together
into a stable matrix,
but it doesn't do a lot for longevity.
And that's that's the problem with
custard bases. But if you're eating your
ice cream after a week, then it doesn't
matter. Just make it and eat it. You
know, you you likely won't see a
difference if you make ice cream and eat
it within a week between one that has
stabilizer in and one that doesn't have
stabilizer in. The only time you will
notice a difference is if your ice cream
base hasn't been calculated properly,
hasn't been balanced, then it's
irrelevant because it's a bad recipe to
start with.
Stabilizers do not help with hardness of
ice cream specifically. They will have a
tiny little effect on it just by the
nature of the viscosity of the base that
you're now making. Without increased
viscosity, it will likely freeze a
little bit harder. Imagine a a U shape.
At one top of the U, you've got no ice,
no stabilizers, loads of water, and the
other one stabilized, not as much water.
Down in the middle is where you need to
be.
The one with loads of water, no
stabilizers will freeze hard as a rock
because everything turns to wise. The
one with too much stabilizer will freeze
hard as rock because it's way too
viscous. Down in the middle is where you
need to be. And that little sweet spot
down there in the middle is created by
the right amount of stabilizers, the
right amount of sugars or sugar
substitutes, the right amount of solids,
the right amount of fats for the recipe,
but ultimately the right amount of water
as well. So, we're going to do some ice
cream calculator reviews now that
there's some new ones out, which is
amazing. We've got some online only
versions of Patrick's ice cream
calculator, which is super exciting.
We've also got a couple of others to to
try. So, we're going to use those in
videos going forward. So, if you want to
know how to balance your ice cream to
make sure that it's really good,
regardless of what machine you use,
whether it's a Ninja Creamy, a
traditional CH machine, or even an ice
bucket with a handle, whatever works, it
always is of benefit to create an ice
cream that is balanced. So, with that in
mind, thanks very much for watching.
Don't forget to like and subscribe, and
I'll see you next time.
[Music]